

Chenliang Huang (黄辰亮)

Associate Astronomer Room 1019, 80 Nandan Rd, Xuhui District, Shanghai, China Shanghai Astronomical Observatory, Chinese Academy of Sciences huangcl@shao.ac.cn https://huang-cl.github.io/

OVERVIEW

I am a theoretical astrophysicist who applies physical laws to understand astronomical phenomena. My primary research interest is studying the physics and chemistry of the middle and upper atmosphere of gas giant exoplanets, as well as their escape, through both the analysis of observations and theoretical modeling. Additionally, I have constructed an interior structure model of terrestrial exoplanets to constrain their compositions, and a radiative transfer model to study the physics of interacting supernova remnants.

EMPLOYMENT

Associate Astronomer

2023-

Shanghai Astronomical Observatory, CAS

- Atmosphere of gas giant exoplanets and their escape.
- Characterize the interior structure of terrestrial exoplanets.

Postdoctoral Research Associate

2019-2022

University of Arizona

• Characterize exoplanet upper atmosphere using its atomic absorption features.

Postdoctoral Scholar

2017-2019

University of Nevada, Las Vegas

• Model the interior structure of terrestrial super-earth planets.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Astronomy

2011-2017

University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA

"Spectral Line Formation in Hot Jupiter Atmospheres and in Interacting Supernovae"

Thesis advisor: Arras, Phil / Chevalier, Roger

B.S. in Physics

2007-2011

Peking University, Beijing, China

PEER-REVIEWED JOURNAL PAPERS [ADS publication list]

- 16. Pai Asnodkar A., Wang J., Broome M., <u>Huang C.</u>, et al., "PEPSI's non-detection of escaping hydrogen and metal lines adds to the enigma of WASP-12 b", <u>MNRAS</u> 535, 1829 (2024).
- 15. Sreejith, A. G., France, K., Fossati, L., [and twelve others, including Huang, C.], "CUTE Reveals Escaping Metals in the Upper Atmosphere of the Ultrahot Jupiter WASP-189b", ApJL 954, 23 (2023).
- 14. ★ Huang, C., Koskinen, T., Lavvas, P., Fossati, L., "A hydrodynamic study of the escape of metal species and excited hydrogen in the atmosphere of the hot Jupiter WASP-121b", ApJ 951, 123 (2023).
- 13. Cubillos, P. E., Fossati, L., Koskinen, T., Huang, C., et al., "The Hubble/STIS near-ultraviolet transmission spectrum of HD 189733 b", A&A 671, A170 (2023).

- 12. * Huang, C., Rice, D. and Steffen, J. H., "MAGRATHEA: an open-source spherical symmetric planet interior structure code", MNRAS 513, 5256 (2022).
- 11. Koskinen, T. T., Lavvas, P., <u>Huang, C.</u>, et al., "Mass Loss by Atmospheric Escape from Extremely Close-in Planets", *ApJ* **929**, 52 (2022).
- 10. Grande, Z., Pham, C.H., Smith, D., [and eight others, including <u>Huang, C.</u>], "Pressure Driven Symmetry Transitions in Dense H₂O", *PRB* **105**, 10 (2022).
- 9. Fossati, L., Young, M.E., Shulyak, D., [and five others, including <u>Huang</u>, C.], "Non-local thermodynamic equilibrium effects determine the temperature structure of the ultra-hot Jupiter KELT-9b", A&A 653, 52 (2021).
- 8. Huang, C., Rice, D. R., Grande, Z. M., et al., "Implications of an improved water equation of state for water-rich planets", MNRAS 503, 2825 (2021).
- 7. Yan, D., Guo, J., Huang, C., and Xing, L., "Atmosphere Escape Inferred from Modeling the Hα Transmission Spectrum of WASP-121b", ApJ 907, L47 (2021).
- 6. Yan, F., Wyttenbach, A., [and 25 others, including Huang, C.], "Detection of the hydrogen Balmer lines in the ultra-hot Jupiter WASP-33b", A & A 645, A22 (2021).
- 5. Oza, A. V., Johnson, R., [and 13 others, including <u>Huang</u>, C.], "Sodium and Potassium Signatures of Volcanic Satellites Orbiting Close-in Gas Giant Exoplanets", *ApJ* 855, 168 (2019).
- 4. * Huang, C. and Chevalier, R. A., "Electron Scattering Wings on Lines in Interacting Supernovae", MNRAS 475, 1261 (2018).
- 3. \star Huang, C., Arras, P., Christie, D. and Li, Z.-Y., "A Model of the H α and Na Transmission Spectrum of HD 189733b", ApJ 851, 150 (2017).
- 2. Borish, H. J., <u>Huang, C.</u>, Chevalier, R. A., et al., "Near-infrared Spectroscopy of the Type IIn SN 2010jl: Evidence for <u>High Velocity</u> Ejecta", *ApJ* 801, 7 (2015).
- 1. Liao, J., Zhou, Y., <u>Huang, C.</u>, Wang, Y., Peng, L., "Fabrication, Transfer, and Transport Properties of Monolayered Freestanding Nanoparticle Sheets", *Small* 7, 583 (2011).

NON PEER-REVIEWED

 Schlawin, E., Ilyin, I., Feinstein, A. D. [and 5 others, including <u>Huang</u>, C.], "H-α Variability of V1298 Tau c", RNAAS 5, 195 (2021).

INVITED TALKS

• "A hydrodynamic study of the atmospheric escape of the hot Jupiter WASP-121b"	
Youth Innovation Promotion Association, NAOC, Beijing	April 2024
• "A hydrodynamic study of the atmospheric escape of the hot Jupiter WASP-121b"	
Tsinghua University DoA Colloquium, Beijing	March 2024
• "A hydrodynamic study of the atmospheric escape of the hot Jupiter WASP-121b"	
Exoplanets & Planet Formation 2023, Beijing	December 2023
• "MAGRATHEA: An Open-Source Planet Interior Structure Code"	
2023 Meeting of Planetary Sciences, Tengchong	November 2023
• "A hydrodynamic study of the atmospheric escape of the hot Jupiter WASP-121b"	
University of Chicago	October 2023
• "A hydrodynamic study of the atmospheric escape of the hot Jupiter WASP-121b"	
University of Virginia	October 2023
• "A hydrodynamic study of the atmospheric escape of the hot Jupiter WASP-121b"	
55th DPS conference, San Antonio, TX, USA	October 2023
• "A hydrodynamic study of the atmospheric escape of the hot Jupiter WASP-121b"	
ET seminar, virtual	June 2023
• "A hydrodynamic study of the atmospheric escape of the hot Jupiter WASP-121b"	
Beijing Normal University, Beijing	June 2023

• "A hydrodynamic study of the escape of metal species and excited hydrogen in the atmosphere of the hot Jupiter WASP-121b" 2023 International Conference of Deep Space Sciences, Hefei April 2023 • "MAGRATHEA: An Open-Source Planet Interior Structure Code" 5th Young Scientist Forum of Planetary Science, Sanya March 2023 "A hydrodynamic study of the atmospheric escape of the hot Jupiter WASP-121b" CIERA, Northwestern University, Chicago, IL Dec 2022 • "A hydrodynamic study of the hot Jupiter WASP-121b and an open-source planet interior structure solver MAGRATHEA" Shanghai Astronomical Observatory, virtual May 2022 • "A hydrodynamic study of the escape of metal species and excited hydrogen in the atmosphere of the hot Jupiter WASP-121b" National Astronomical Observatory of China, virtual May 2022 • "Theoretical Landscape of Atmospheric Escape" Exoplanet IV, Las Vegas May 2022 • "A hydrodynamic study of the escape of metal species and excited hydrogen in the atmosphere of the hot Jupiter WASP-121b" Origins Seminar, Steward Observatory March 2022 • "A hydrodynamic study of radiative cooling and escape of metal species in WASP-121b atmosphere" Steward Early career scientist talk, virtual March 2021• "A hydrodynamic study of WASP-121b atmosphere" CUTE science team meeting, virtual December 2020 • "Model of the interior structure of terrestrial planets" Steward Symposium, UofA, Tucson, AZ November 2019 • "A Model of the H α and Na Transmission Spectrum of HD 189733b" UW Madison, Madions, WI September 2019 • "Electron Scattering Wings on Lines in Interacting Supernovae" Peking University, Beijing, China July 2018 • "Introduction to the Study of Exoplanet Atmospheres" Theoretical Physics Division, IHEP, CAS, Beijing, China February 2016 • "Modeling of Hot Jupiter HD 189733b Hα Transmission Spectral Line" Peking University, Beijing, China February 2016 **HONORS & FUNDINGS**

• Shanghai Pujiang Program October 2023 • Shanghai Overseas High-level Talents (Youth) May 2024